[Music]
what's up friends
now i just finished filming an epic
three-part
mega series on all things muscle
hypertrophy so today i thought i would
give you a
very condensed version of parts one and
two
the physiology of that big three-part
series
if you want to see more about what's in
those other videos you can see the
outlines
here i'm not going to cover all this
ground in this particular video but i
wanted you to see what you're missing in
the other ones
okay this is the video the part one when
i cover the physiology
part two is what we call the mechanism
so what are the signals
that tell you to grow muscle and then
part three
is a practical application so eating and
training and all that stuff
now what's particularly special about
this series is we've learned
so much new information in the last
three years if you haven't really been
paying attention
you probably have missed some things or
you're a little bit behind so i wanted
to make this big series
so you can all be as up-to-date as
humanly possible
let's go ahead and jump right into it
then and talk a little bit of the
condensed version
of the physiology of muscle hypertrophy
so if you want to know about how
muscle grows we have to first understand
what's in muscle
we know that the things that you look at
on the outside are actually a composite
of millions of individual muscle fibers
and if we were to go in with a little
needle get my joke there
take some of that muscle sample out this
is what it would look like
and fits in fact this is that process
i'm describing this is called a skeletal
muscle biopsy
you can see the needle right there and
that little red part in the middle
is the actual muscle sample so it's
about 100 milligrams or so and this is a
fairly painless and
and not very difficult process procedure
to recover from i've done it
thousands of times well that's a lot
hundreds hundreds of times
may actually maybe close to a thousand
and if i were to pull that little red
thing out of the middle and line it all
up like that
this is what you would see in fact the
picture there is from a world champion
athlete and i won't tell you any more
about who that is
and there's probably a couple of a
thousand fibers in what you're seeing
there
looks pretty high grade right so if
you're to take that tissue and put it in
a petri dish here
uh the color kind of goes away for a
bunch of reasons you don't care about
but you can see right up here
these are a bunch of individual muscle
fibers
i don't have the time to get into it
today but you can see very quickly what
it would look like
under microscope so i've dyed the muscle
green here and then watch up at the top
i will pull out two individual muscle
fibers from that little bundle
and it's it's as easy as that okay i'll
actually separate them for you so you
can see them one by one
in fact if i were able to hold that up
you could see
them with your naked eye so they're
pretty big the muscle cells
skeletal muscle is some of the largest
cells in all of biology
especially the ones in humans so they're
very very unique like that
so if you can imagine an entire muscle
pick whichever one is your favorite your
gastroc your soleus your rectus
abdominis i don't care
and that's that blue circle like we say
to the minerals is thousands or millions
well certainly at this point millions of
individual muscle fibers
and those are wrapped together into
groups with connective tissue and we
call those groups fascicles
now i'm going to get rid of that for now
because it's not super important but i
do want to acknowledge
that's really how the muscle works so
within each individual muscle cell we
have a bunch of what are called
myofibrils
and then within each individual
myofibril
you have all a whole bunch of what are
called myofilaments
okay and this is what if you've been to
exercise physiology class
this would be your actin and your myosin
now in the part one when i go into depth
i explain a lot about what's actually
growing how and where and why
but i'm going to hit the highlights here
okay like i said this is a different
image
just so you can conceptualize the whole
muscle the fast the whole muscle the
fascicle the muscle fibers
all the way down to those myofibrils as
well as the actinomyosin
and those form what we call sarcomeres
okay this is a little more in-depth look
uh of that myosin and the actin and the
way that your muscle contracts is
through a process we call the sliding
filament theory
where basically you use some energy your
myosin reaches up grabs actin and pulls
it to the center line
so it goes like that pulls everything
closer together your muscle stacks up
and like i said this is an actual image
of an individual muscle fiber
the blue the horizontal thing this is
real this is of course made in
powerpoint but this is
actually real and the cells themselves
are quite large
this is a different way to look at it
this is in cross section so now each
individual circle is a muscle fiber and
you can see this is from my colleague
jimmy bagley
and the green ones are the fast twitch
fibers
the yellowish ones are the slow twitch
fibers and
what we know is generally the fast which
fibers are bigger especially with
strength training
now there is some natural variability
person to person so not all fast twitch
fibers are always larger than slow
stretch fibers
but generally that's the case in fact
one of the things jimmy and i have seen
quite consistently is if you do a lot of
steady state long duration endurance
training
it's pretty common for those type 1
fibers to be equal if not larger
than the type 2 fast twitch fibers
okay but in general the fast twitch
fibers respond pretty well
to strength training they like to grow
all right if they're activated and this
the slow church ones
grow as well but perhaps not as specific
um
but there's some detail behind that that
we have to get to so what's actually
growing
well you have really two possible
options if your bicep is bigger now
after two months of training hard
either one of two general things
happened the fibers got longer
or the fibers got whiter and so if we
look at what longer would mean
you can see the image i think this is a
great job from a recent review article
that's free by the way you can look at
this title and go read this article if
you want and it explains in great detail
what muscle hypertrophy really is
great work by by stu phillips and troy
hornberger
just fantastic researchers in the field
but nonetheless you can imagine because
each individual muscle cell
does not run the entire length of the
whole muscle
so your biceps say one of the the
brachialis or brachioradialis whichever
one you wanted
okay the the muscle might run from there
there
but the fibers don't run from there they
only maybe go halfway or a third or
quarter or something like that
and so you can see the image being
depicted here if they actually grew in
length that would actually
increase the the diameter uh of the
muscle cell so that's one possible
option and we would generally call that
increasing sarcomere in series
so those sarcomeres i talked about where
the myosin actin run
you would stack them up in series and
the fibers would grow longer now
important distinction
this does not mean your muscle is
getting longer just the muscle fibers
within them
okay in order to actually grow your
muscle longer you're going to have to do
some pretty crazy things it's not going
to be a normal response type of hp
training
so if we come to a little we'll build a
little scorecard here we'll see that
length
okay yes it kind of happens there but
there is some detail that we're not
exactly sure about
and it's not a muscle getting longer
it's the fibers that are possibly
getting longer
going to option number two which is what
we call the diameter in
the scientific field this would be
called also radial or
cross-sectional area i'll use diameter
from here on out but those are those
those are what those terms are if you
come across them in the research
and we know very clearly and there is
abundant research to show
this is very common finding okay the
fibers will increase in diameter
what we don't know exactly is how that's
happening and that's what that whole
part one video
is it's like an hour and describing what
we know specifically about
how it grows in diameter i'll give you
the short version here
so option one with increasing the
diameter of the whole muscle
is if you increase the number of fibers
within it okay
now you have a couple of options to do
that so you can see from the image
if you had say five fibers that your
whole muscle would be that thick but if
you had six fibers it'd be
thicker pretty obvious to understand how
that would work seven you get even
thicker and thicker so by increasing the
number of fibers you increase the
diameter of the whole muscle
well it turns out that's what we call
hyperplasia and it's
probably fairly unlikely and i remember
being taught that it's impossible
and thinking really
i don't think the story is quite that
easy and that was over 20 years ago
and i've been actually on record
everywhere you can imagine talking about
hyperplasia and the fact that i just
never
thought it was impossible well we've
learned some
things in the last just couple of years
to dramatically increase our
understanding of hyperplasia
and so here's what we're looking at if
you go back to our basic schematic and
you have the whole muscle there
all the individual muscle fibers all the
myofibrils within it and the
myofilaments
hyperplasia would be if you just added
new fibers
and that's probably fairly unlikely to
happen especially with
normal strength training hypertrophy now
with aging like and well
puberty and developing as a little baby
and stuff like that okay it's possible
but
we're talking a normal strength training
adaptation is probably unlikely
however there's another concept called
fiber splitting or branching
and a recent review article about my
friend kevin
has shown that this is a fairly normal
response to extreme loading
and you can see that happen right here
this is one individual
this is an image from kevin's paper one
individual muscle fiber there at the top
and you can see it's being brand it's
starting to branch or split
there so it's not that you're growing a
whole new cell but you could in theory
be taking one cell and split it
into multiple so that the net result
would be an increase in total number of
fibers
the mechanism though is not what we call
bona fide
hyperplasia so not growing a new cell is
splitting
it's a bit of a semantic argument there
but in our field of science it is an
important distinction
okay so you'll see this again called
splitting or fragmenting or branching or
something like that
in fact if you go back to 2006 there's
actually this has been demonstrated in
humans
at least they thought so um classically
that that fiber right there is thought
to be a branched or splitted
a split splitted muscle fiber now this
is from
power lifters with a known use of
anabolic steroids and we honestly
haven't followed this up
much at all so i think there's a lot of
questions i don't think there's clearly
a lot of questions remaining regarding
fiber splitting if you go back to
kevin's paper we see that it happens
with extreme overload
what's that mean exactly well most of
our research is coming from animals like
rodents
where we can say take out their their
left leg effectively and make them walk
only on their right leg for four months
okay that's not a that's extreme
overloading but that's not realistic so
the question we really have is does this
happen with strength training
we don't really know yet right we have
to get more information on that
i'm going to hedge my bet i think it
does i don't think it happens in six
weeks of training i don't think it
happens in six months
i do think folks that are six years 10
years
15 years into the training i do think
they have gone through significant
hyperpla uh
fiber splitting i almost i'm sorry and
they have more fibers
so i don't have that scientifically but
that's my intuition okay regardless
i think we have to say okay muscle
myofiber and muscle fiber hyperplasia is
not impossible
it's probably just very uncommon and not
explaining most or even a significant
portion of your actual muscle
hypertrophy
okay but i'll still put it as a question
mark because there are a lot of answers
we still need okay the other option then
to get your muscle bigger if you're not
adding more fibers is to grow the
diameter of the muscle itself
and again we know that it would look
like this instead of adding more fibers
you just
make each one you have thicker so if you
go back to our similar image here
from uh troy and stews and as well as
ken
apologize for not putting in the first
time there kent
it would look like this okay so we see
section b here probably not likely
that's the fiber splitting
but this is more likely to be the
scenario for our radial or diameter
growth
and muscle muscle fibers and again we
have seen this now
i mean probably 30 40 50 times at least
maybe probably more than that honestly
in the in the research very highly
documented that the muscle fibers
themselves
increased in diameter this would be what
we call then start increasing the
sarcomeres in parallel
okay now it's never actually really been
shown the sarcomere thing but the muscle
fibers get larger okay so the summary to
all this
is the myofiber the muscle cell itself
getting
increasing is one of the most
long-standing and widely acknowledged
contributors of re or
resistance exercise induced muscle
hypertrophy
and what we see is somewhere in the
neighborhood of 10 to 35 percent
increase in size after
two to three months or four months of
training now you wouldn't ever see that
much of an increase in the whole muscle
size so we do have a bit of a
disassociation between
changing the cell size and changing the
actual muscle size so don't get caught
up and mixed up if you're reading the
research there
and how much they actually grew okay
so like we said the real in and a lot of
the things i laid out in part one
is the mystery still becomes what's
actually growing in the cell itself to
make it bigger
it could be what we call myofibrillar
hypertrophy so the myofibers the yellow
things within it
could be growing in size okay we don't
necessarily know that yet
it could be an increase in what we call
contractile protein accretion
so that would be referring to the
myofibrils the
myofilaments actin and myosin so maybe
you're just adding
thicker myosin in other words there's a
certain amount of protein associated
with the myosin filament maybe if you
make that larger
it grows that would make then complete
sense why oftentimes there's an
association between growing more muscle
and getting stronger you have more
contractile elements you make more cross
bridges
more force production those are very
highly associated
it could be sarcoplasmic hypertrophy
which means an increase in the cell size
that are coming from the non-contractile
units
this would mostly be things like water
and this would explain why
although there's an association between
getting bigger and getting stronger
it's not always the case so the
strongest people in the world are not
necessarily the biggest people in the
world
right i.e powerlifters being incredibly
strong bodybuilders being strong but not
as strong
potentially the slightly different ways
they train cause a slightly different
type of
of muscle fiber hypertrophy one being an
increase in the contractile units one
being an increase in the non-contractile
units
or probably more realistically just a
slight change in their percentage
that's coming from each that explains
the muscle science grow
and we have some information that's
growing mike roberts at auburn
cody hahn are doing fantastic work in
that area of sarcoposm and hypertrophy
but we don't know yet and we're
certainly nothing definitive so when
more research is needed or in theory it
could come from myofibular hyperplasia
or splitting now
again that's not muscle fiber but the
fibrils themselves
could either hypertrophy which is
probably unlikely but they could also
just simply be splitting which is
i think not shown but i think is very
very likely
okay now i know i left you with a lot of
things of mystery and you're like you
didn't really explain it to us
well one thing i can tell you is we have
been limited by technology for a long
time but those days are almost over
and so you can see actual image of a
laser i'm shooting into a muscle fiber
right there so
the imaging technologies we're getting
are becoming really really high quality
and really cheap
well cheap er and so we're going to have
an explosion of research in these areas
that we've been stagnant in for 60 years
a lot of these questions i showed you
people have been asking again since the
60s or 70s or 80s that passed
and i honestly think we're gonna have
answers in the next handful of years
uh barring any more worldwide pandemics
and
the west coast burning and all this
other stuff so
nonetheless so to summarize the
physiology here
uh the fibers change in the pinnation
angle and they can lengthen so that's
that first one right so the length of
them could get longer and that would
potentially be adding sarcomeres
in series although it's never really
been shown specifically
that's what we think happens fiber
hyperplasia or splitting is probably
unlikely certainly hyperplasia i think
splitting is likely but
more a long-term adaptation not a
short-term bond
and then three fiber hypertrophies by
increasing the sarcoplasm or the
contractile
which could be coming from the
myofibrillar hyperplasia or hypertrophy
but we don't know the details
specifically in this area
so now that i've hit you with the very
basics of what hypertrophy is
let's talk about how we maximize it in
other words
how do we make the body stimulate muscle
growth
that's really what we're after so that's
let's jump into the quick version of
part two regardless of how the muscle
grows
which we're still working out we know
that it takes a four-step process
to induce that growth whatever part that
is okay
and so why call these the four steps to
activating muscle growth
number one you have to have some sort of
stimulus two you have to activate what
we call a signaling cascade that has to
cause your nucleus to want to express
the genes that regulate
and control protein synthesis so that
you can build
this new protein myosin actin myofiber
whatever it happens to be
so this is sort of what we call the
central dogma
of tissue growth right in general but
this is applied to muscle hypertrophy
so we'll go through each one of these
steps fairly quickly and the first one
is a stimulus
i didn't say stimulant
get it dead joke anyways
what we're talking about is something
has to tell the the muscle fiber
that it you need to get bigger faster
stronger whatever the case might be
right
and this happens at the level most
likely of the cell membrane or the
outside of the muscle fiber
now in 2010 a young and up-and-coming
scientist
named brad schoenfeld proposed and he
said hey i think there's three main
quote-unquote mechanisms
or things that cause your body to induce
muscle growth
and you don't necessarily have to have
all three one would work
maybe combining a couple is more
effective or not
but regardless either three of these are
an option and he basically said that
could be their mechanical tension
which you could think of as the cell
wall being stretched because it's being
asked to lift something heavy
it could be metabolic stress this could
be
you know fatigue the burn oh my gosh i'm
feeling lactate build up
all these things right go watch my
lactate video that's not how it works
but
i'm trying to help you understand the
basics here or it could be muscle damage
right i'm sore the next day so well
10 years have now gone by since brad's
original study and he just released
another review and
update on what he thought last year and
so
i explained that in depth in part two of
that series but here's the basics
okay we know that again you imagine
you've got a muscle cell
and these three little cylinders on the
outside are different
sensors if you will and we know a lot
more detail about what
these sensors are what they're
responding to but here's basically what
it would look like
you have what we would call
mechanosensors and these are the things
that are going to that are going to
sense the stretch
okay so this is where mechanical tension
comes in or damage or edema
right so now we have a mechanism on the
cell wall that is explaining both
mechanical tension as well as muscle
damage
over here you've got things like
anabolic hormones testosterone
igf-1 etc now we do know testosterone
clearly plays a role in stimulating
muscle growth anyone who's ever taken
exogenous testosterone is very clear
shocker it works okay look at mark bell
testosterone works however
it is not a direct and is not a linear
express or co inducer if you will of
growth such that
uh if you do one type of workout and
that causes you to have more of an
anabol or a
testosterone surge in another one that
doesn't mean anything
related to muscle hypertrophy similarly
if you take two people and one has more
testosterone in their blood than the
other one
that doesn't mean the person with more
testosterone will get more muscle growth
so the post exercise
surge if you will so the amount the up
the increase of testosterone you get
from an
acute workout it doesn't hardly do
anything in fact the research
would suggest it does it plays almost no
role in causing muscle growth
this is why you don't see it on that
original list from brad and i actually
think the research is fairly clear
here it doesn't do much so i'm not
saying testosterone is not playing a
part in muscle growth
it has to be there clearly if you don't
have testosterone you will not grow
but once you've reached a certain
minimal level
going higher testosterone doesn't cause
any additional growth
unless you go extremely high with things
like exogenous or foreign
testosterone and now the concentration
is just such a such a magnitude that you
would never see
endogenously and so you get muscle
growth
the third one is we call metabolic
stress and these are the sensors on your
cell wall for things like lactate
hypoxia
again this is the burn this is the pump
all of those things would explain
how it can cause your muscle to grow
if that works and you get an uh an
adequate signal
step two then you have to move into the
cell itself so the
step one happened at the cell membrane
step two happens when we call the
cytoplasm so
inside of it and what you have to do
then is activate
what we call a signaling cascade so you
have a whole bunch of proteins
whose job is to transmit a signal from
those receptors
or the cell wall all the way to the
nucleus okay because remember the
nucleus is what holds your dna and
controls your cell tells it to grow
shrink thy repair
etc so there's a little protein whatever
it happens to be and i'm
not even worth explaining to what it's
called that sits on the cell wall
or close to it something happens that
activates that sensor and of course
there would be a protein right here and
a protein right there
i'm just using this one for explanation
purposes that protein would activate
another protein through things called
kinases
um this is the most common of these
proteins is called
mtor very highly associated with muscle
hypertrophy
and again we would generally call that
cell signaling in this case
since the cell signaling response causes
muscle growth we call that anabolic
anabolic meaning grow
tissue size right one of those proteins
would eventually hit the cell wall
or the nucleus wall if you will and it
would then tell it
and give it the signal says hey we think
you should start growing more
muscle size this
like i said the nucleus holds your dna
and tells it what to do
if that whole thing is activated we get
a certain response
so now cell signaling can kind of be in
this context can be broken up into
three major categories now in reality
it's thousands of categories
you have signaling for all kinds of
things but for muscle growth
we have a whole cascade that causes the
anabolic side okay this is a
akt mtor sort of global pathways we'll
call it
we have also a catabolic which is
breakdown and this is a foxo and
nf kappa b and all this stuff okay but
then you'll also have another one in the
middle
which is an inhibitor it's not doesn't
cause growth and it doesn't cause
breakdown
but it blocks growth and this is really
important because this is how we make
sure we don't
grow tumors right so you want to have a
gas pedal you want to break
right and then you also want to be able
to break down the tissue so the
catabolic side is important because once
you've damaged tissue
you've got to break it down and get it
out of there anabolic cause more growth
inhibitors are hey let's stop growing
because the growth is getting out of
control
cancer tumor and the most famous
inhibitor
is myostatin and this is of course like
all these they have genes as well as
proteins but
you can google around and read more
about what myostatin is but
there are many animals and some humans
now that have been found that are just
naturally born
with the mutation and they don't have
the gene or enough of the gene
to code for the protein of mtor or
myostatin
and so they don't have a lot of this
floating this protein floating around
and so they get this kind of
uncontrolled muscle growth and so these
pictures you're seeing here
are they're not they haven't been given
steroids or antibiotics or anything
you're thinking
they were just born with this crazy
mutation and so they just grow muscle
non-stop all right pretty cool stuff
and for the record they tend to live
just fine no damage
okay if you convince the nucleus to then
grow
to do its thing it's going to start
expressing its genes and you can go back
to molecular biology but
and remember what that actually means
but in the case of growing muscle it
would say
hey we've got a whole bunch of genes
that code for all kinds of things
let's start coding and replicating the
ones that make say myosin
and there's actually a study that came
out just last year fantastic
suggesting they think there's only about
141 different
genes that are be associated with muscle
hypertrophy
which is crazy considering there's like
20 000 genes or something
141 is a very small number but more is
coming out of it
if you convince the cell to do that the
next level is then to actually go
through protein synthesis so you have to
activate
that process by using what are called
the ribosomes so the ribosomes are
another little organelle that kind of
would sit outside the nucleus
and you would take amino acids you would
put them together
in the ribosomes you know amino acids
slap together makes a polyp a peptide
take those together make it a
polypeptide smash those together
you make it a protein so the ribosomes
are the ones that are really actually
making your muscle bigger
so if you can imagine this being that
that myosin filament
i talked about it could be any protein
but just imagine it to be that
if you had enough amino acids around of
the right ones these ones would be the
essential amino acids
and very specifically leucine derives
this
but all of the senseless amino acids are
needed so you would take them
you would send them to the ribosomes the
ribosomes would start combining them
together
and start spitting up new proteins so
that process right there would be what
we call protein synthesis so you're
bringing together
synthesizing proteins
okay so if you want to know whether or
not you actually grew muscle you have to
balance
the anabolic side with the catabolic
side because both are going on
and so this is just a theoretical
example of how you could increase
breakdown of the muscle increase the
growth a little bit so your net balance
would actually be negative you would
lose tissue here
another way to do it would be you know a
massive stimulate a stimulation of
growth
a little stimulus there and your net
would be almost the exact same thing
so we have a totally different thing
that happened but the net result was
almost identical
or you could have something like this
and then that result could actually be
negative
and so really pay attention to
supplements or training programs or
anything if they're saying hey we've
studied this in a lab and shown
our product increases muscle protein
synthesis
well if you didn't pay attention to the
catabolic side of the breakdown then i
don't actually know what the net result
is going to be
and spoiler alert all you care about is
that pink part what's the protein
balance
okay so if you want to add muscle
as we finish up here you have to do a
couple of things
you have to train appropriately and in
part three the whole
video i explained to you what that
actually means in painstaking detail
why well you have to give yourself a
reason to grow okay you have to do
something that sufficiently activates
the signaling cascade
sufficiently activates gene expression
and then sufficiently activates
protein synthesis but none of that's
going to work if you don't eat
appropriately right why because you have
to have
fuel to do the actual training if you
don't have the carbohydrates or the fat
or whatever you're using to power the
workout
that ain't going to matter because
you're never going to cause that cascade
unless of course you take testosterone
but then you also have to have to
carbohydrates to pro to power this
process so one of the things that we
know
is protein synthesis is very
specifically powered by carbohydrate so
you want to make sure that those are
available
when you have the signal to grow or when
that signal is maximized
but then you also have to have the
building material which would be the
amino acids
so you have to have carbohydrates and
fat to power the workouts
probably carbohydrates optimally
power the actual molecular process of
building proteins
but nothing's going to get built if you
don't have the amino acids around to be
built
in the first place so if you look at
this as a summary of bioenergetics as we
wrap up
and let's say you ate some carbohydrates
and in your exercise physiology class
you were taught about how that's broken
down in the krebs cycle
and you give off some carbon dioxide you
make some atp and you use that to do
your sliding filament theory
right there okay great he did that and
that caused some sort of stimulus
could have been tension could have been
damaged could have been stress
regardless how it did it it went to the
muscle cell
on the outside and caused some sort of
activation of a protein
that protein activated another protein
and we globally called that signaling
proteins
that went to the nucleus and said hey
start expressing your dna or your genes
for muscle tissue okay great then we
went to the ribosomes and we started to
activate this protein synthesis
process however you also then because
you're a good
studious boy and girl you had not only
carbohydrates to power your workout but
you had some protein
the protein then don't aren't really
used to make atp
we use those as materials so those amino
acids are floating through your body
again leucine and the specifically the
essential amino acids
get taken up into the tissue they're
available so when the ribosomes need
them
they can start taking them breaking them
down from their whole
protein source into amino acids the
amino acids then go to the ribosomes and
they can get added on to your new
protein
and bada bing you went from that
to that
now i think i did a pretty damn good job
i've taken you through the physiology
and the molecular mechanisms
that signal muscle growth and i stayed
pretty close to this 25 minute mark it
took me almost three hours to do it in
the other videos
so hopefully you enjoyed that condensed
version
i'm tired i'm gonna go take a break
we'll see you on the other side
cheers everyone